All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is מ"ג. Mem
Gimmel. Thank you to people who alerted me that the audio wasn't
working so well on the video. I just needed to change the
settings. So, always good to know. Apparently, I had not had the
mic activated. All right, so today's דף Daf is מ"ג Mem Gimmel
and we pick up at the bottom of מ"ב עמוד ב'. Mem
Bet Amud Bet. And basically, what we're dealing with is
what we're trying to
understand in a משנה Mishnah in שבועות Shavuot is a debate about
the חכמים Chachamim and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon about whether somebody is
חייב Chayav קרבן שבועה Korban Shavuah on a קנס. Knas. And although
that debate seems to be not really a principal debate but about
whether we assume when the father is suing somebody and claiming somebody
raped his daughter, whether he's presumed to be demanding the קנס, Knas,
the fifty, or presumed to be demanding the ממון. Mamon. Nevertheless, the
גמרא Gemara hones in on רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon as a position
that says that this money is קנס, Knas, the fifty שקלים Shekels
is קנס Knas and therefore exempt from קרבן שבועה, Korban Shavuah, and
wants to explore according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, to what extent
does that money retain its identity of קנס? Knas? And does it
retain its identity of קנס Knas even after העמדה בדין? Ha'amadah Be-din?
Even if the person is suing and saying that you originally raped
my daughter and then there was a court case, and would he
still be, and he denies it, would he still be חייב Chayav
a קרבן שבועה? Korban Shavuah? Is it still have an identity of
קנס Knas even after העמדה בדין Ha'amadah Be-din or does העמדה בדין
Ha'amadah Be-din convert it into ממון? Mamon? And the נפקא מינות Nafkah
Minas are: if you admit, are you חייב? Chayav? Is there a
קרבן שבועה? Korban Shavuah? Can the person, if he dies, bequeath it
to his children and so on? So רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's position,
both in our משנה Mishnah and that משנה, Mishnah, seems to be
that it always remains to be קנס. Knas. However, רבא Rava said
that no, it actually gets converted to be ממון, Mamon, and the
גמרא Gemara until now has identified, basically made the cases that he
sounds like it's still קנס Knas as an exception. So by קרבן
שבועה, Korban Shavuah, we have an exception. There's a special פסוק Pasuk
וכחש Ve-kichesh to tell us that even after העמדה בדין, Ha'amadah Be-din,
it retains קנס; Knas; it's exempt from a קרבן שבועה. Korban Shavuah.
And in our משנה, Mishnah, if the father dies, then it doesn't
pass on to the sons. The daughter actually is entitled to collect
it. That's also based on a special פסוק Pasuk about כסף שלו...
Keseph Shelo... excuse me, about ונתן האיש. Ve-natan Ha-ish. So basically, though,
in all other cases, when we're not dealing with קרבן שבועה, Korban
Shavuah, when we're dealing with a קנס Knas that isn't the fifty,
then after העמדה בדין, Ha'amadah Be-din, it gets converted into ממון. Mamon.
That is our take claim about רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Is it
שבועה?
Shavuah? The קרבן Korban itself is considered to be a קנס? Knas?
No.
No, but you don't bring a קרבן Korban for denying a קנס.
Knas. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי. Ei Hachi. So
we pick up about thirteen lines from the bottom. Line starts with
the word לחוד ונתן לחוד. Le-chud Ve-natan Le-chud. And then it says
אי הכי. Ei Hachi. אי הכי, Ei Hachi, תלמוד לומר Talmud Lomar
וכחש. Ve-kichesh.
If according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon generally the point is that
is that this thing here is, at least when it comes to
the fifty שקל, Shekel, it's fundamentally still a קנס Knas even regarding
the issue about being מוריש לבניו, Moris Le-banav, then why did he
quote by the קרבן Korban the פסוק Pasuk of וכחש Ve-kichesh that
makes it sound like it's a specific exception by קרבן? Korban? תלמוד
לומר Talmud Lomar ונתן Ve-natan מיבעי ליה. Miba'ei Lei.
He should have at least when you're dealing with the fifty שקל
Shekel quoted the פסוק Pasuk of ונתן Ve-natan to say that it's
completely excluded from the category of קנס, Knas, whether to pass on
to one's children, like you or whether for the purpose of this
קרבן שבועה. Korban Shavuah. I don't want to belabor this point. It's
whatever. So אמר רבא: Amar Rava: כי איצטריך וכחש, Ki Itzterach Ve-kichesh,
כגון שעמדה בדין ובגרה ומתה. Kegon She-amdah Be-din U-bagrah U-meitah.
Okay,
so now just to add another twist and a complication. Basically, we
said that the fifty שקל Shekel not only by קרבן Korban is
an exception; everything by קרבן Korban is an exception and still considered
a קנס. Knas. But we said the fifty שקל Shekel by everything
is considered to be a קנס Knas according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. So why therefore by the fifty שקל Shekel did we have
an extra, did we need also the פסוק Pasuk of וכחש Ve-kichesh
to exclude it from קרבן? Korban? Why couldn't you just say fifty
שקל Shekel is always considered a קנס Knas according to רבי שמעון?
Rabbi Shimon? So it gives one scenario where even the fifty שקל
Shekel for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would be considered to be ממון.
Mamon. What would be that scenario? So it's כגון, Kegon, let's read
it again: כי איצטריך קרא, Ki Itzterach Kra, כגון שעמדה בדין ובגרה.
Kegon She-amdah Be-din U-bagrah.
So basically there was a court case, then she became a בוגרת.
Bogeret. So therefore in that case, the העמדה בדין Ha'amadah Be-din didn't
yet fully convert it into ממון. Mamon. But somehow there's an assumption
here, don't ask me why, that once then she also becomes emancipated
and a בוגרת, Bogeret, in that case then the obligation becomes not
to the father but to her. Then somehow, since it's not ונתן
לאבי הנערה Ve-natan Le-avi Ha-na'arah but it's about giving it to her,
then somehow it plus the העמדה בדין, Ha'amadah Be-din, it would be
considered ממון. Mamon. And in that case
then she dies and her father inherits from her. So in that
case actually the father is going to get it, but he's going
to get it as ממון Mamon because there was a העמדה בדין
Ha'amadah Be-din and she became emancipated. דהתם כי קא ירית אביה מינה
דידה קא ירית. De-hasam Ki Ka-yaris Aviha Minei Didah Ka-yaris. דהתם כי
קא ירית אביה מן דידה קא ירית. Dehasam ki ka yarish aviya
min d'idka yarish. When you have to, so what that has to
do with in that case you need the פסוק pasuk of וכחש
v'kichiesh to say that even though here רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does
agree that it actually would be ממון, mammon, nevertheless since it started
as קנס, knas, which if we learned from וכחש v'kichiesh that there's
never going to be a קרבן שבועה, korban shvuah, even when it
a hundred percent becomes ממון mammon in other areas as well. Okay,
let's just finish the line. The גמרא Gemara will say, אי הכי
יצאו אלו שהן קנס. i hachi yatu eilu shehein knas. What does
he mean that he says you don't bring a קרבן korban on
this because it's a קנס? knas? ממון הוא. mammon hu. You're giving
me a scenario where even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would agree that
it's ממון, mammon, that it's transferred to the daughter and from the
daughter back to the father. So in that case, why are we
calling it a קנס knas and exempting it from a קרבן שבועה?
korban shvuah? So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק יצאו אלו שעיקרן קנס.
amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak yatu eilu she'ikaran knas.
No, what it means is that at least they started their life
as a קנס. knas. Okay, so that was complicated and again I
don't want to belabor it, but the basic point is that רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you never bring a קרבן שבועה korban shvuah
on something that started its life as a קנס knas even if
it changed into ממון. mammon. Okay, and he we created an interesting
scenario where because where you have this case that not only is
there העמדה בדין hamada badin but then the daughter becomes a בוגרת
bogeres and somehow that means that it now changes into ממון. mammon.
So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says two things. Number one is he
says by the קרבן שבועה, korban shvuah, it,
well let's start it this way. Normally what the claim is is
that after העמדה בדין hamada badin it does convert into ממון. mammon.
It really is ממון mammon and you can be מוריש לבניו. morish
levano. And if you admitted in court that there was a העמדה
בדין hamada badin you'd have to pay. It is ממון. mammon. However,
by קרבן שבועה korban shvuah there's an exception according to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon that even though it is ממון mammon if it started
its life as קנס knas there's no קרבן שבועה. korban shvuah. That's
one exception. Okay, yes, forever. Yes, it's ממון, mammon, if you admit
you're חייב, chayav, you know, you can bequeath to your kids, but
but you're not חייב chayav a קרבן שבועה. korban shvuah. There, וכחש
v'kichiesh tells you if it started its life as קנס knas you're
פטור. patur. So then there's another exception that by the fifty שקל
shekel that is given to the father that is the one thing
that even after העמדה בדין hamada badin remains קנס. knas. And that's
why in our משנה Mishnah רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that if
the father dies before it's collected it doesn't go to the kids,
the daughter is allowed to collect it. So that's an exception that
it really does remain קנס knas and even within there we say
there's a scenario that it could become ממון mammon which is that
the daughter becomes a בוגרת, bogeres, then it becomes ממון mammon even
according
to רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. Okay.
And you won't have to bring a קרבן korban because of וכחש.
v'kichiesh. Okay, so that was a little complicated but I think we
get the basic idea. So now let's move on. The גמרא Gemara
says like this. איתיבי, Eisiv,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon פוטר שאינו משלם קנס על פי עצמו. poter
she'eino meshallem knas al pi atzmo. So it says רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon exempts from the קרבן korban in a case where the father
says, you know, give me the fifty שקל shekel because you don't
pay a קנס knas based on your own admission. So it sounds
like it's really a קנס knas and it sounds like you wouldn't
pay it based on your own admission. It doesn't just sound like
because it started its life as a קנס. knas. So טעמא דלא
עמד בדין. taama d'lo amad badin. And that sounds like that the
only reason you're not going to pay according to רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon or bring a קרבן korban is because it still is a
קנס knas because there's no העמדה בדין. hamada badin. הא עמד בדין
דמשלם על פי עצמו, Ha'amad badin demishallem al pi atzmo, once there's
העמדה בדין hamada badin and you're saying that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
agrees that once it's העמדה בדין hamada badin it becomes ממון mammon
and you would pay based on your own admission, it sounds like
קרבן שבועה נמי מתחייב korban shvuah nami mitchayev that you would bring
a קרבן. korban. So it sounds like not that רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says it's exempt because it started its life as a קנס.
knas. It sounds like if it's now a קנס knas you're פטור,
patur, if it's become ממון, mammon, if there's העמדה בדין hamada badin
you'd be חייב. chayav. So the גמרא Gemara says רבי שמעון לדיבריהם
דרבנן קאמר להו. Rabbi Shimon lidvireihem deRabbanan qamar lehu. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon is responding to the רבנן. Rabbanan. לדידי, Ledidi, as far as
I'm concerned, אף על גב דעמד בדין, af al gav de'amad badin,
even if it was העמדה בדין hamada badin and it got converted
into ממון, mammon, רחמנא פטריה, Rachmana patrei, the Torah exempted you, מוכחש,
miv'kichiesh, וכחש v'kichiesh tells you that it has to know me from
וכחש. v'kichiesh. The Torah tells you it has to have started its
life as ממון. mammon. אלא לדידכו, Ella ledidchu, but you who say
that as long as now it's ממון mammon you bring a קרבן
שבועה, korban shvuah, אודו לי מיהת היכא דלא עמד בדין, odu li
mihat heicha d'lo amad badin,
at least you should concede when he's demanding for the case of
rape to be paid the father but if there's not yet העמדה
בדין hamada badin at least you there you should concede to me
דכי קתבע קנסא קתבע. deki katava knas qatava. There it really is
קנס. knas. Okay, so fine. ומודה בקנס פטור, U'modeh biknas patur, and
if you would admit you'd be פטור, patur, so there shouldn't be
a קרבן שבועה. korban shvuah. Top of מג עמוד א. mem gimel
amud aleph. So the גמרא Gemara says רבנן סברי Rabbanan savrei and
the רבנן Rabbanan hold
no,
כי קתבע, ki katava, the guy is just saying you owe me
for raping my daughter, בושת ופגם קתבע, boshes upgam qatava,
he's not really asking for the קנס, knas, the father's really demanding
the בושת boshes and the פגם. pgam. Okay, so then as I
said it's not really a principled discussion it's just what's implicit when
he says you raped my daughter, is he saying pay me the
קנס knas or is he saying pay me the בושת ופגם. boshes
upgam. I don't know why we're not assuming he's saying pay me
both. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this. במאי קמיפלגי. Bemai kamipalgi.
They just got emotionally involved, that's why.
So what are they debating in terms of how to interpret what
the father is demanding? אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Pappa רבי שמעון
סבר, Rabbi Shimon savar, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds, לא שביק איניש
מידי דקייץ ותבע
מידי דלא קייץ.
lo shavik inish midi dekaitz v'tava
leidi d'lo kaitz. A person won't abandon the thing that has a
fixed amount, fifty שקל shekel is very concrete, you know exactly what
you're demanding, and say you have to pay me for בושת boshes
and פגם pgam where it's not determined how much that's going to
be and that's too amorphous. It could be more. Exactly, like I
mean if you know that courts pay millions of dollars. other awards
for pain and suffering, you don't care whether it's קייץ kayatz or
not; you're going to be demanding the one that's going to be
the bigger payoff anyway. Okay, that's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds,
so he says implicitly you're demanding the קנס. knas. ורבנן סברי לא
שביק איניש מידי דכי מודי ביה לא מיפטר. v'rabanan savri lo shavik
inish midi de-chi modi bei lo miftar. No,
a person isn't going to abandon something that the guy can't get
out of by conceding to, right? So you're going to demand the
ממון mamon because the ממון mamon is something that there's no way
out of it. And if you get the guy to confess and
admit, then you're going to get paid. So that's the one you're
going to demand, that maybe I'll force the guy to admit to
it. So you're not going to abandon that ותבע מידי דכי מודי
ביה מיפטר v'tava midi de-chi modi bei miftar and demand something that
even if he admits to it, he's still going to be exempt
and then he might even be exempt even after witnesses come. Okay,
so there's one debate whether the father goes and says to the
guy, where you know you raped my daughter pay me up, and
he denies and makes a שבועה, shvua, whether it's about the קנס
knas aspect of the payment or the ממון mamon and again why
we can't assume both I don't know, that's the debate over the
רבנן rabanan and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, but what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is that רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon actual position is and
again none of this is really clear that even after העמדה בדין
ha'amada bedin you remain exempt from the קרבן korban even though it's
ממון mamon because it started its life as קנס. knas. Nevertheless, getting
back to our משנה, mishna, the חידוש chidush of רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon is that even after העמדה בדין ha'amada bedin by the fifty
שקל, shekel, it's not yet considered ממון mamon owned to the father,
it's still considered a קנס knas and therefore if the father dies
before it's been collected, the daughter is entitled to collect it. Okay,
so that is really bracketing the whole קרבן שבועה korban shvua which
is not really our topic at all, something to learn when we
do שבועות. Shvuos. The interesting thing for our topic is that his
position that even after העמדה בדין ha'amada bedin the fifty שקל shekel
is not payable directly to the father, it doesn't become a straight
monetary debt to the father, but it remains its identity of קנס
knas going through the daughter and if the father dies before it's
collected, it's the daughter that gets paid, yes.
Sorry I just was trying to think this through in terms of
process, presumably the court would issue a ruling, then there'd be some
sort of documentation for this. So if the plaintiff comes with this
documentation for it, all right fine, now it's all over, shows him
the documentation, and the guy admits to it, it's not considered מודה
בקנס modeh biknas anyway, right?
Right, so that's what when we're going to get to that idea
מודה בקנס פטור modeh biknas patur and פטור patur even for witnesses
that come later. The exception to that is רואה עדים ממשמשים ובאים,
ro'eh edim memashmeshin uva'in, right, if you see that you're about to
get proof brought against you and then you admit to the קנס.
knas. Again, your admission will never obligate you, but it won't also
get you out of it for later. So if you know that
there's court documentation that might be a case of רואה עדים. ro'eh
edim. Right, exactly.
Okay, yes, why is קנס knas and קרבן korban linked conceptually?
Well because the normal explanation is just you only bring a קרבן
שבועה korban shvua on something that your denial got you out of
it, that had that you should have admitted and that therefore you
would have been obligated. By קנס, knas, even had you admitted you
wouldn't have been obligated, so your denial doesn't carry the same type
of weight, right? The guy says where's the money you owe me
and you deny and take a שבועה, shvua, the denial isn't even
so meaningful in a case where the admission itself wouldn't obligate. So
the basic idea is that it's not because of קנס knas per
se but it's because of case as the גמרא Gemara is saying
דכי מודי מיפטר. de-chi modi miftar. That here I am I'm saying
you owe me money and the fact is you're using God's name
to back up your denial and that's like a type of a
trespass against God or whatever you bring a קרבן korban all those
things, but that's only when your denial mattered. If your admission also
wouldn't have obligated you, then it's not so the whole case isn't
so meaningful, right? But רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon basically says that I
don't even if it's a case where your denial your admission would
have obligated you, it's been converted to ממון mamon somehow it's a
categorical exclusion because it started its life as קנס. knas. So that's
more arbitrary. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. That was complicated
but we're done with that. Now we get on I mean to
a new topic. It's a related one, but at least it's a
new one. Dope, it's good to have you back. Good coffee.
That's good coffee. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay,
בעי מיניה רבי אבינא מרב ששת. ba'ei minei Rabbi Avina me-Rav Sheshet.
So רבי אבינא Rabbi Avina asks רב ששת Rav Sheshet following question:
בת הניזונת מן האחין. bat hanizona min ha'achin. A daughter that is
supported, you know, food support by the brothers. Her father is dead.
Now what does it mean that she's supported by the brothers? One
of the תנאי כתובה tenai ketubah is the following, is that every
husband standard writes in his כתובה ketubah to his wife that after
I die, any daughter, so after he dies the sons inherit the
estate. What's going to happen about the daughters? Until that point the
father has been you know having the daughter live with him in
the house, I mean they're his daughters too they you know and
basically feeding them and so on. And then they're going to get
married and then they'll be taken care of, right? This was the
nature of patriarchal society, taken care of financially and otherwise by their
husband. Well that's all very nice when the father's alive. What happens
when the father is dead? Okay, so
therefore who's taking care of the daughter's interests? And they don't inherit,
so who's taking care of their interests? So the same way the
כתובה, ketubah, one of its main functions as we discussed the other
day, you know, is to be there as a type of a
financial cushion for the wife since also she doesn't inherit, so I
mean in the case of divorce it serves like an alimony payment,
in the case of death it serves as a substitute for an
inheritance, so therefore it provides
payout or over time. So here too, she can either take her
lump sum
payment or—that's such a hard decision to make.
Or I know, I know. That hundred million dollars. Anyway, so, but
either she takes her lump sum payment or she gets supported by
the estate and gets put, you know, she gets the housing and
the food and supported by the estate in terms of her like
day-to-day needs until she decides to take her lump sum payment, but
until that point she's supported by the estate. So that's the wife.
It serves as a cushion and a protection, a substitute inheritance. And
for the daughters as well, a standard תנאי כתובה tnai ktuvah is
that the husband would write to the wife any daughters that I
have from you, you know, they will be supported by the estate
until they go ahead, until they get married. Okay, so that's the
case called בת הניזונת מן האחים. Bat Hanizonet Min HaAchim. The daughters
supported by the brothers. Not like the brothers have a choice; that's
part of the conditions of the כתובה ktuvah that the estate supports
them.
But in the actual כתובה? ktuvah?
That's in the actual כתובה, ktuvah, or it would be considered a
תנאי כתובה tnai ktuvah even if it weren't written, it would be
considered just to be assumed. Okay, and that's finally somewhere in this
מסכת כתובות Masechet Ktuvot we're actually going to get to what the
כתובה ktuvah looks like and
what its different sort of conditions are or pieces are. Anyway, so
there she is. She's supported by the estate, and the question is,
who now is entitled to her earnings? Because the normal principle is
that the father, מעשה הבת לאביה, Maaseh HaBat L'Aviha, the father gets
the earnings of the daughter. So now when the estate is supporting
her, maybe in exchange—the brothers? For a קטנה? ktanah? Right, for a
קטנה. ktanah. Correct, for a קטנה נערה. ktanah naarah. Now that the
estate is supporting her, maybe she should go ahead and maybe the
estate should get her earnings. Now I want to say one other
point about the difference between the father and the husband.
By the case of the husband, the husband is not entitled to
his wife's earnings. The husband, and the—that is rabbinic. And the rabbis
basically created a
reciprocity, and the reciprocity is that the husband agrees to support the
wife in terms of, you know, lodging and, what's it called, room
and board, and in exchange, he gets any earnings that she makes,
whether she goes out and hires herself out as a seamstress to
the larger community or whatever she would do, or whether like any
work she does within the house that's for the benefit of the
household, and in exchange, she gets supported by the household. That would
be your standard כתובה, ktuvah, so it would be an exchange. So
logically that you apply that model to the case of the brothers
and you would say the brothers, the estate is supporting her and
therefore they should get her earnings. But that is not the model,
as we're going to see soon, by the father. The father, the
Torah gives him a unilateral right to his daughter's מעשה ידיים maaseh
yadayim earnings. How do you know? Because what can a father do
with his daughter?
Sell her as a slave.
Sell her as a slave, which is basically selling the right to
her earnings, selling her as a—and she wouldn't be like an עבד
כנעני. eved knaani. She wouldn't be owned totally as property, but the
person who bought her would basically have ownership over her earnings and
could direct her and tell her what she had to do. So
the father has unilateral rights to the daughter's earnings. He biblically does
not have an obligation to actually provide for his kids, which is
not only daughters, sons as well. Okay, so the fact that a
child, you know, that a parent, I mean, it's beyond at least
the first few
years, a parent—five years old already got to kick them out and
put them into, you know, that's what they would do. At five
years old, they would be, what's it called,
what's it called when you send the kids out to learn from
an expert? Apprentice. They would apprentice themselves to someone. Anyway, so it's
not the same type of reciprocal relationship. He really has unilateral rights.
Now, and he supports his kids, it's basically considered a type of
an act of חסד, chesed, which raises, by the way, parenthetically, interesting
צדקה tzedakah questions. If somebody is basically poor, very poor, can they
use like מעשר כספים maaser kesafim to pay for their own child
care, for their own costs in terms of providing for their kids
since they're not legally mandated to actually provide for their kids? Anyway,
okay.
But what are they legally mandated to do?
Have kids. Okay, so all right, so anyway, that's the question. So
here she is, she's supported by the estate, and the brothers have
no say in it. Do they get her earnings? On the one
hand, that would sort of parallel the relationship with a husband and
wife, but it doesn't exactly parallel the unilateral relationship between the father
and the daughter. So what's the story? Let's take a look.
Okay, so בעי מיני רבי אבין מרב ששת, Ba'ei minei Rabbi Avin
meiRav Sheshet, בת הניזונת מן האחים, bat hanizonet min ha'achim, the daughter
that is supported by the
brothers, מעשה ידיה למי? maaseh yadeha lemi? Who gets her earnings?
במקום אב קיימי? Bimkom av kaimei? So do we say that the
brothers are in the place of the father because they're now representing
the father's estate? מה התם מעשה ידיה לאב, Mah hatam maaseh yadeha
l'av, the same way the father would get her earnings, הכא נמי
מעשה ידיה לאחים, hacha nami maaseh yadeha l'achim, here too the brothers
get her earnings.
או דילמא... od dilma... It's not similar to the father. התם *Hatam*,
and here's why it's not, not only in a formal legalistic sense
is it not the same relationship, but also there's a logic. התם
מדידיה מזנא *Hatam mididei mitzana*, there she is fed by his own
earnings. The father goes out, makes money, earns money, and uses some
of that money to pay for his daughter's upkeep. הכא לא lo,
מדידהו מזנא *Hacha lo midedahu mitzana*, they're not being fed by their
earnings, they're just being fed by the estate that they inherited, right?
So therefore it's not exactly unilateral. In one case the father actually
earns money and uses that money to pay for his daughter's upkeep.
Here they're not being, you know, they're being supported by the pre-existing
estate, not by their own earnings. And more than that, רש"י Rashi,
*Rashi* also points out that they don't even have a say in
the matter, right? As I said, the father technically doesn't have an
obligation to feed the daughter. So if he's feeding the daughter, he's
doing it out of his own goodness of heart, whereas here they're
feeding the daughter, they don't have a choice. That's one of the
conditions on the estate. So maybe therefore they should not be entitled
to her earnings. So wait a second, what...
does the obligation survive the
estate?
No, that is correct, it's not a personal obligation, it's only on
the estate itself. Now of course you could say fine, let the
money go not directly to the brothers, let the money go to
replenish the estate or something of that nature, but nevertheless it is
different because when the father does it he does it at a
free choice. Here there's no choice.
Wait, if he didn't support her while he's alive, קל וחומר *kal
v'chomer* he shouldn't have to
support her when he's dead, wouldn't you think? Yeah, but he accepted
that obligation upon himself. Now could be the Rabbis instituted that as
a standard obligation to accept upon yourself?
But didn't they institute that when she's alive also?
Because they assumed that people would do the normal
thing, right? Okay, so... I mean I assume if they saw that
that was a problem they would have instituted that. Alright, so what's
the question? That's a nice interesting question. אמר ליה תניתוה *Amar lei
tani tu'a*, we learned it. What's learned in a משנה mishnah. *Mishna*?
אלמנה almana ניזונת מנכסי יתומים *Almana nizonet minichsei yetomim*,
the widow is supported by the property of the estate of the
heirs. ומעשה ידיה שלהן *U'ma'aseh yadeha shelahen*, and in exchange, implicitly whatever,
they get her earnings. So you see that's it, if you're supported
by the estate, the same way the widow's earnings goes to the
estate, the daughter's earnings should go to the estate.
But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
מי דמי *mi dami*, how can you compare it? אלמנה almana לא
ניחא ליה בהרווחה *Almana lo nichla lei b'harvacha*, בתו ניחא ליה בהרווחה
*bito nichla lei b'harvacha*. Maybe his widow, he's not so interested in
her, you know, making a nice profit. If she makes any money
let it go back to the estate, he doesn't, you know, his
care for his wife doesn't sort of survive his death. Okay, after
he passes away, if she's going to earn any money let it
go back to the estate. בתו *Bito*, but his concern for his
daughter, ניחא ליה בהרווחה *nichla lei b'harvacha*, he wants her to make
some profit, and therefore he would want his daughter to be fed
by the estate and any money she earned he'd like her to
pocket. So it's a very interesting assumption that people's concern for their
kids more survives their death than their concern for their spouses. So
let's see, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to challenge that. למימר
דבתו עדיפא ליה מאלמנתו *L'meimar d'bito adifa lei mei'almanato*, means that his
daughter is of a greater concern to him than his widow? If
that's true, והאמר רבי אבא *v'ha'amar Rabbi Abba*, אמר רבי יוסי *amar
Rabbi Yosei*, עשו אלמנה almana אצל הבת כבת אצל האחים *asu almana
etzel habat k'bat etzel ha'achin*. They made the relationship of the אלמנה
almana *almana* to the widow, to the בת bat, *bat*, like the
relationship of the בת *bat* to the אחים *achin*. What does this
mean? בנכסים מועטים *B'nichasim mu'atim*, if there's a very small estate. So
it's going to spell out what this means. מה בת אצל אחים
*Ma bat etzel achin*, if you've got a daughter and brothers and
it's a very small estate and there's only barely enough to basically
pay for the daughter's support and then the brothers won't inherit anything,
right? Because all the money is going to go for the daughter's
support. Not only will they not inherit anything, they won't even have
enough money to put food on the table from the estate. Nevertheless,
you give precedence to the daughter. Okay, what do we say, what
about the widow?
We're about to say that. Okay, so what do we say בנכסים
מועטים *b'nichasim mu'atim*? מה הבת אצל אחים הבת ניזונת והאחים ישאלו על
הפתחין *ma habat etzel achin habat nizonet v'hachin yishalu al haptachin*. In
the same way if the small estate we use whatever moneys there
are to pay for the daughter's upkeep and let the brothers go
ahead and let them go begging. Okay, now one way to understand
that is just that there's a lien on the estate. So any
debt to the estate, of which the obligation to the daughter is
a debt, takes precedence over them liquidating the estate. Nevertheless, you should
say, but shouldn't they be entitled to be fed by the estate
equal to the daughter, forget inherit? So the point is fine, but
it's more of a degradation for a daughter to go begging than
it is for the sons to go begging. So therefore the daughter
gets precedence. So the daughter gets fed by the estate and they
have to go begging.
Even for everyone's a minor?
Yeah, that's just the rule. We'll see more about that later, but
that's the rule. Okay, so that's true if it's a daughter and
brothers. Similarly, אף אלמנה almana אצל הבת *af almana etzel habat*, let's
say it's a very small estate and there's not enough money to
pay for the upkeep of both the widow and the daughter. So
what's the story, who gets precedence? אלמנה almanah, ניזונת *almana nizonet*, it's
the widow that gets supported, והבת תשאל על הפתחין *v'habat tishal al
haptachin*, and the daughter has to go begging. So the same way
the daughter has precedence over the brothers, the widow has precedence over
the daughter. So you see that we assume implicit in the conditions
of the כתובה, ketubah he's giving greater precedence to the widow. So
why shouldn't we say the same thing here about the idea that
if an, that by the earnings, that if the widow's earnings, she
doesn't get to keep, so certainly the daughter, she shouldn't get to
keep because we see he has greater concern for his widow. So
the גמרא Gemara, says, לעניין זילותא, le-inyan ziluta, when it comes to
being like, you know, degraded, so like you know going out begging,
exactly, אלמנה עדיפא ליה, almana adifa leh, he's more concerned that his
widow shouldn't have to endure this type of a shame, denigration and
shame, okay, than his daughter. לעניין הרווחה, le-inyan harvacha, but when we're
not talking about anybody being shamed, we're just talking about them earning
some nice money and pocketing some money, בתו עדיפא ליה, beto adifa
leh, maybe he's more concerned that his daughter should earn the money
and any money she earns she should keep, rather than his wife,
his wife earns money, let it go to the estate. I cannot
begin to understand how the priorities shift between whether it's an issue
of זילותא ziluta or הרווחה. harvacha. It seems like a very, you
know, it seems like the גמרא Gemara could have said the exact
reverse if the evidence had been reversed, but okay, whatever.
Yeah, what's their suggestion?
So he's interested in the daughter's dowry and...
Oh that's interesting. You want the daughter to get married, right? So
he wants her to earn some extra money, and he doesn't necessarily
want his wife to get remarried or something, oh that's interesting. Why
though the זילותא ziluta wouldn't affect her marriage prospects so it's not
clear, but anyway, that's a nice explanation, that when it comes to
actually putting aside extra money, he wants his daughter to be able
to put aside extra money and to keep her earnings in order
to be a dowry, that's a nice idea.
Yes, just a simple question. All these women, the אלמנה almanah. or
the בת, or I guess this is the בושת, boshet, neither of
them are a בוגרת, bogeret, they're all at least...
No, no, no, the אלמנה almanah isn't, the אלמנה almanah. is...
Right,
that was my question, so I didn't think so either, the אלמנה
almanah is a grown adult woman, exactly. So you're telling me that,
just to clarify, so even a woman could be forty-five years old,
her husband dies, she goes back under the household of her father?
No, we're not talking about the household of her father, she's supported
by the dead husband's estate. Dead husband's.
Instead of getting, instead of getting a piece of the inheritance, she
gets either the כתובה ketubah payout or, until she chooses to get
the כתובה ketubah, payout, she gets supported by the estate. So you
can just...
גובה, gova, right, כתובה, ketubah supported indefinitely.
So
the
father's now out of the picture totally, he's...
Well, he's dead,
okay.
No, the husband...
I mean the husband's dead, right, the father's out of, the father
is irrelevant, right. The father is irrelevant. Okay, so let's continue.
Though at what time though, then like you know, how do you
expect like a ten-year-old boy to be any more than a ten-year-old
girl?
I don't know, the ten-year-old boys would go out and apprentice themselves.
So would the בית דין beit din not get involved in this
kind of a case?
I mean they would if they would need to be. Okay, we'll
see all about this later, okay. This is going to be, you
know, this is going to be the, the actual conditions, the actual
pieces of the כתובה kesuvah. are going to be like very soon
in the גמרא, Gemara so we're already get, getting a foretaste of
it. Let's continue. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay. So
now we're claiming, so yes the אלמנה's almanah, earnings go to the
estate but the daughter's we're claiming maybe she gets to keep. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. מתיב רב יוסף, Metiv Rav
Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef asks
based on our משנה. mishnah Now we see why it's brought in,
because our משנה mishnah. said that even according to רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon who says that it remains the fifty שקל shekel remains a
קנס knas and if the father dies it goes to the daughter,
but he says when she earns money and let's say she hasn't
collected her salary yet and the father dies before, then once she
had earned the money, the money passes down to the brothers. That's
ממון, mamon, that as soon as the money is earned the debt
is incurred directly to the father, and if the father dies it
goes to the brothers as opposed to what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
said about קנס. knas. So let's see how that plays in.
This is a קנס. knas.
Right, yeah exactly. מעשה ידיה ומציאתה, Maaseh yadeha u-metziatah, her earnings and
found objects, אף על פי שלא גבתה, af al pi she-lo gavtah,
even if she hasn't collected her paycheck yet, once she earned the
money it's a debt to the father and in that case, מת
האב, met ha-av, even if the father died, הרי הן של אחים,
harei hen shel achim, it goes to the brothers and in that
way it's different for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon than the קנס knas
where as long as it's not collected it goes to her. טעמא
דבחיי האב, Taama de-ve-chayei ha-av,
the reason
presumably that the money is going to go to the brothers, to
the estate, is because she earned the money while the father was
alive. That's through, that's basically the assumption of the משנה. mishnah, Since
she earned it while he was alive, it became a debt to
the father and transfers to the brothers. טעמא דבחיי האב, Taama de-ve-chayei
ha-av, הא לאחר מיתת האב, ha le-achar mitat ha-av,
had she earned money, it sounds pretty strongly from the משנה, mishnah
had she earned the money after the father died, right, it sounds
very much that לעצמה, le-atzmah, that she would keep it, right? The
whole point of the משנה Mishna is since she earned it when
the father's alive the debt passes down to the brothers, but if
she earned the money after the father was dead it sounds like
she would keep it. So that makes it very clear that she
keeps her earnings. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. The
גמרא Gemara says, מאי לאו במזונות, mai lav bizonet, aren't we and
wouldn't we even be talking about a case where she's being supported
by the estate, and nevertheless she would keep her earnings after the
father died? לא דשאינה ניזונת, lo dishaina nizonet, no, it's a case
where she's not supported by the estate. Let's say there's absolutely no
money in the estate and she's not supported, in that case she'll
keep her earnings after the father died. But when she is being
supported by the estate, maybe the earnings will go to the estate.
Why doesn't the age difference matter between the comparison of these two
cases? In one case she was an אלמנה, she was a בוגרת,
bogeret, here she's a קטנה. ktana.
We're not talking about אלמנה. אלמנה was only brought in to compare
to the קטנה ktana case. Our question is about קטנה, ktana, not
about אלמנה. So does קטנה's ktana earnings go to the estate?
So we were saying that our משנה Mishna says that it does,
at least theoretically we're saying it does. And our משנה Mishna says,
strongly says that it doesn't, that the only reason it would pass
to the brothers is if she earned it when the father was
alive. But if the daughter earned it after the father died, the
implication is it doesn't go to the estate. Now we're not talking
about the אלמנה anymore, we're still talking about, we're focusing on the
daughter.
The point is our משנה Mishna makes it clear that the daughter's
earnings would go to her if she earned it after the father
had died. And the גמרא Gemara says, well fine, but maybe that's
talking about a special case where she's not being supported by the
estate. But if she is being supported, it would actually go to
the estate. So the גמרא Gemara says לא דשאינה ניזונת. lo dishaina
nizonet. אי בשאינה ניזונת, ee bishaina nizonet,
if she's not being supported by the estate, מאי למימרא, mai lememra,
then it's not a חידוש. chiddush. The גמרא's Gemara assuming that the
primary, the basic הלכה halacha that if she, that the money that
she
earns when the father's alive would transfer to the brothers isn't the
חידוש. chiddush. The חידוש chiddush would be the implication of the משנה
Mishna that if she earned it after the father died, she keeps
it. So the גמרא's Gemara. saying if it's a case where she's
not supported by the estate, it would be obvious she would keep
whatever money she earned after the father died. Why would that be
obvious? Maybe, maybe not. Maybe the same way the father's entitled to
her earnings even though he doesn't have to support her, maybe even
if the estate isn't supporting her, maybe the estate is entitled to
the earnings. So the גמרא Gemara says no, that would be obvious.
Why would that be obvious? לא דשאינה ניזונת. lo dishaina nizonet. מאי
למימרא, mai lememra, אפילו למאן דאמר, afilu leman de'amar,
here's why it would be like obvious that the estate wouldn't get
it if she wasn't being supported. Because even according to the opinion
that יכול הרב לומר לעבד עשה עמי ואיני זונך, yachol harav lomar
l'eved asay imi v'eini zoncha,
there is, same way the father's entitled to his daughter's earnings and
he doesn't have a legal obligation to support her, there's a debate
about the story about your slave, about your, whether you are entitled
to say to your slave,
your non-Jewish slave, whether you're entitled to his work without any obligation
to feed him and support him. It's an interesting question. Like in
the South pre-Civil War, was there a legal obligation on the masters
to feed their slaves, to support them, or would it just be
that they would just be wasting their property if they wouldn't take
care of them? Presumably there wasn't a legal obligation. So that's a
debate in the גמרא. Gemara Is there a legal obligation to feed
your slaves, or can you say to your slave work for me
and I won't support you, which is this very unilateral relationship. So
even if that is true in the case of a slave, הני
מילי בעבד כנעני, hani mili b'eved Kna'ani,
that's by a non-Jewish slave דלא כתיב עמך, delo ktiv imcha,
it doesn't say that he shall be with you. You don't have
a real obligation to take care of him. אבל בעבד עברי, aval
b'eved Ivri, but by a Jewish slave, of which the daughter is
no worse than even though she could be sold as a slave
she's sold as a Jewish slave, דכתיב עמך, d'ktiv imcha,
with you he shall dwell, לא, then you cannot say work for
me without me paying you. כל שכן בתו, kol sheken bito, certainly
the daughter. Now again, it is interesting because the rabbis did not
technically obligate the father to support the daughter. But nevertheless, certainly in
the case when it comes to the brothers, it's inconceivable that the
brothers would be entitled to her earnings without supporting her. Basically what
we have is the following. Our משנה Mishna makes it clear, if
she earns money when the father's alive, then that money goes down
to the brothers, which basically is almost black and white saying if
she earns money after the father is dead, it doesn't go to
the brothers. So it's pretty clear that she pockets her money, and
it doesn't go to the estate. And you can't tell me it's
a case where the estate isn't supporting her, because then it's obvious.
If the estate wasn't supporting her, of course she keeps her money.
You wouldn't have to say that. So it obviously is a case
where the estate is supporting her, and nevertheless it tells you that
she's entitled to keep her money. So that is the argument that
she's entitled to keep her money. So the גמרא Gemara still wants
to resist that. אמר רבא בר עולא לא נצרכה אלא להעדפה. Amar
Rava bar Ula lo nitzrecha ela l'hadafa. No, there's a way out
of that. We could be talking about the extra earnings. What does
the extra earnings mean? It means the money that goes beyond the
cost of her upkeep. Meaning maybe the הלכה halacha is that the
daughter, are you right that the משנה Mishna makes it sound like
she keeps her earnings? Yes. But maybe she keeps her earnings that
go exceed the cost of her upkeep. If basically her food bills,
food and dorm bill and lodging bills are a hundred dollars a
week. Okay, when we say who keeps the money, let’s say she
earns $150, $150 a week and the cost of her upkeep is
$100 a week, right? So,
so maybe she pockets the whole 150. There’s another possibility. The other
possibility is is that she pays back the 100 that were the
cost of her upkeep and she only pockets the additional 50. Everybody
with me here? Right? So what it’s saying is, did you prove
from the משנה Mishna. that the daughter is entitled to keep the
earnings that she earns when the father is dead and presumably even
in a case when she’s supported? Yes, you proved it. But maybe
that doesn’t mean she keeps all the earnings. Maybe she only keeps
the amount of the earnings that exceed the cost of her upkeep,
but the first amount of money that she earns, she has to
pay back the estate for the cost of her upkeep. She would
only get to keep the additional amount. So you haven’t really proved
anything from the משנה. Mishna, We wanted to know if she could
keep every single penny that she earns.
Okay. Does that make sense? Because I mean if the תנאי כתובה
tenai ketubah is for her to be supported, so then what...
that’s... okay, that’s the argument. Or do we say bottom line is
she’s supported, but if she can earn money and pay back that
amount of support, then she has to. Okay, so we concede the
fact that she’s entitled to the העדפה, hadafah, additional earnings. But the
question is, is she entitled to the earnings that would pay that
would be the cost of her upkeep or does that have to
go to replenish the estate? All right, so that’s the question. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: להעדפה, L'hadafah,
the additional earnings. So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
so Rava said: גברא רבא כרב יוסף לא ידע דאיכא העדפה? Gavra
raba k'Rav Yosef lo yada d'ika hadafah?
This great person, Rav Yosef, didn’t realize, meaning why would the גמרא
Gemara feel that this was such a problem and then finally you
needed somebody to tell you, oh, we’re talking about the additional earnings?
Right? How is it that Rav Yosef, who’s the one that was
challenged with this, didn’t realize... like who raised the question from our
משנה, Mishna? how is it he didn’t realize that there was an
easy answer, that we’re talking about additional earnings and that clearly would
be the money that she would everybody would agree she would get
to pocket? Why did he think there was a question from our
משנה? Mishna Of course our משנה Mishna, could be talking about the
additional earnings. וקמותיב תיובתא, v'kamotiv tiyuvta,
he’s asking a question from our משנה, Mishna, of course he knows
that there’s the idea of additional earnings which everybody agrees she’s entitled
to keep. אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, so Rava said: רב
יוסף מתניתין גופא קשיא ליה. Rav Yosef matnitin gufa kashya leh. No,
Rav Yosef had a better question from the משנה, Mishna. not just
the implication that she could keep it, which maybe is just talking
about the additional earnings. But here’s his question from the משנה. Mishna.
דקתני: Dekatani: מעשה ידיה ומציאתה, ma'aseh yadeha u'metziatah, her earnings and found
objects, אף על פי שלא גבתה, af al pi shelo gavtah, even
before she’s collected them, מציאתה, metziatah, you know, גבתה, gavtah, you know,
would be owed to the father and transfer to the brothers once
she earned it. It becomes a debt to the father if the
father was alive. So here’s what bothered him about the משנה. Mishna
מציאתה ממאן גביא? Metziatah m'man gavya?
What do you mean before she’s collected her found objects? You could
say before she’s collected her paycheck. She earned her money, the father’s
alive, it’s a debt to the father. Now, even if the father
dies, it transfers to the brothers even before she’s collected her paycheck.
That’s about a paycheck that you have to collect. You’ve earned the
money. But how can you say and any found objects that she
finds before she’s collected it? How do you collect a found object?
Okay? So מציאתה ממאן גביא? Metziatah m'man gavya? One second before she
picks it up... אלא לאו, Ella lav,
but she doesn’t own it yet, and the minute she owns it,
she has it. אלא לאו הכי קאמר, Ella lav hachi ka'amar, this
would is what it must mean by combining the two. מעשה ידיה
כמציאתה, Ma'aseh yadeha k'metziatah,
her earnings are like her lost objects. אף על פי. Af al
pi. What does that mean? מה מציאתה בחיי אב לאב לאחר מיתת
אב לעצמה. Mah metziatah b'chayei av l'av, l'achar mitat av l'atzmah.
We take we know that lost objects there was never a question.
Any found objects that she found after the father died, nobody ever
suggested that goes to the estate. Everybody agrees she gets to keep
that. I’ll say why in a minute. So לעצמה. l'atzmah. אף מעשה
ידיה נמי. Af ma'aseh yadeha nami.
So if that’s true, by being putting them in the same category,
what we’re saying is the same way found objects clearly she gets
to keep after the father dies, earnings as well, בחיי אב לאב,
b'chayei av l'av, when the father was alive, he keeps it, לאחר
מיתת אב לעצמה, l'achar mitat av l'atzmah, after the father dies, she
keeps it. So it’s not just that the משנה Mishna implies that
it’s hers after the father is dead, which maybe is only talking
about the additional earnings beyond the cost of the upkeep. It’s the
fact that it packages it together with found objects, and there everybody
it's everybody agrees that she keeps those completely. And therefore, if she
the same way so by putting in the same package, it is
telling you that her earnings as well she totally keeps. So the
גמרא’s Gemara conclusion at this stage is that even though the daughter
is supported by the estate, the same way she keeps her lost
objects once the father is dead, or found objects I should say,
she also keeps any earnings, even the money that would go to
replenish the cost of her upkeep, she gets to keep and pocket.
It does not go back to the estate. Why is it, by
the way, that the found objects is taken for granted that that
is something that does not go back to the estate? So here
it’s interesting, and here’s the idea I was telling you before about
the unilateral aspect. If you take a look at רש"י, Rashi מה
מציאתה, Mah metziatah, about eight lines before the lines get wide, רש"י
Rashi says the
following: דמציאתה פשיטא לן דלעצמה. D'metziatah peshita lan d'l'atzmah. that even if
she's supported by the estate, she gets to keep her found objects.
דהאפילו בחיי אב, dehaafilu bechayei av, even when the father was alive,
לא זכי בהן אב אלא אם כן סמוכה על
שולחנו. lo zachy ban av ella im ken semucha al shulchano. The
father's only entitled to her lost object if he's actually if he's
actually supporting her. כדאמרינן בבבא מציעא, kedamrinan beBava Metzia, which means like
she eats at his table, he's supporting her. ומשום איבה, umishum eivah,
because of hatred, what's the hatred
concern? דכיון דאינו חייב במזונותיה, dekeivan de'eino chayav bimzonoteiha, this is what
I was telling you, as opposed to the husband, the father is
not obligated to feed his daughter. בחייו כדתנן האב אינו חייב במזונות
בתו. bechayav keditnan ha'av eino chayav bimzonot bito. ואי אמרת מציאתה לעצמה,
ve'i amrat metziatah le'atzmah, and if not only here he is he's
supporting her, he's not obligated to, and then any she gets to
keep things that she finds, תו לא יהיב לה מזונות, tu lo
yahiv lah mezonot, then he'll say I don't get it, I put
food on the table, I support her, and she keeps these things
to herself?
So therefore
we what? Everything he's not?
Well, he wasn't so much that well we we it wasn't so
much that well, we can take for granted that he would unless
there would be things that like we don't have to institute a
חיוב, chiyuv, okay, but we do have to try to avoid things
that are going to create problems.
Oh, you found those stickers on the floor right now, not going
to support you.
Yeah, I understand it's a little bizarre, how often do people find
lost objects? But you know, people get annoyed by little things. Here
it is, for the last five years I've been supporting you, you
can't even give me that wallet that you found? Exactly. Anyway, I
can't fully explain it, but it is true that it was not
at the level where we needed to institute a חיוב, chiyuv, okay,
we just needed to avoid certain pitfalls. Anyway, so there,
there, that's clearly because the support of his daughter is volitional. We
had to institute that he's entitled to the מציאה, metzia, to the
lost to the found objects. That would not apply once he's dead.
Once he's dead, the estate is obligated to support his daughter. Since
the estate is obligated to support the daughter, there's no question she
gets to keep her found objects, okay? So she certainly gets to
keep her found objects from the estate because there the whole purpose
of that institution of giving it to the father is no longer
relevant. And if that's true, then we assume also because it's packaged
together, she keeps her earnings as well, and it does not go
even to replenish the amount of her upkeep from the estate. All
right, so that's our conclusion. She keeps it. And now the גמרא's
Gemara going to reinforce that. Let's take a look. איתמר נמי, itmar
nami, it was also taught, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav, בת הניזונת מן האחים, bat hanizonet min ha'achin, a
daughter that is supported
by the brothers, from the estate, מעשה ידיה לעצמה, ma'aseh yadeiha le'atzmah,
she keeps her earnings. אמר רב כהנא מאי טעמא, amar Rav Kahana
mai ta'ama, what's the reason? And this is clearly an אסמכתא, asmachta,
because
well I don't know if it's an אסמכתא, asmachta, let's take a
look. מאי טעמא דכתיב, mai ta'ama dechtiv, והתנחלתם אותם לבניכם אחריכם, vehitnachaltem
otam livneichem achareichem, by slaves, you should bequeath them to your children
after you. אותם לבניכם, otam livneichem, your slaves you bequeath, ולא בנותיכם
לבניכם, velo benoteichem livneichem, but not your daughters to your sons. Again,
the idea that the daughter is a type of a property of
the father, right? Because that's the whole idea about entitled to her
earnings, because he could sell her as a slave, at least as
a Jewish slave, right? אמה עבריה, amah ivriyah, right? So anyway, so
the same way so yes, you bequeath your non-Jewish slaves to your
kids, but you don't transfer the ownership that the father had over
the daughter to the brothers. They now don't have the ownership of
her מעשה ידיים, ma'aseh yadayim, which is an interesting question when the
גמרא Gemara said is the estate entitled to her מעשה ידיים? ma'aseh
yadayim? Was it asking it like as a rabbinic institution? Since the
estate supports her, rabbinically we should give the, you know, say that
her earnings go back to the estate? Or was it saying that
no, maybe the brothers really do inherit the rights that the father
had over the daughter? They can't marry her off the same way
the father could, but maybe they really do have the right to
her earnings, the same way the father had those rights, maybe he
passes on that, you know, that sort of financial interest in his
daughter, maybe he passes on to the brothers. And they're saying no,
no, the פסוק pasuk says that that does not happen.
But if it's really matter of support then they said then you
would have tried to extend the same logic to the widow too,
right? She's supported by the estate, then whatever she finds should go
to the estate to replenish. We don't.
Well, right, but that was the גמרא Gemara before, no, no, it
actually does, her earnings do go to replenish the estate and that
was the גמרא Gemara contrasting the widow to the daughter, right? Okay,
so the
גמרא Gemara says, מה שנתן המוריש זכות בתו לבנו. mah shenatan hamorish
zechut bito livno. מתקיף לה רבה, matkif lah Rabbah, ואימא בפיצויי הבת
וקנסה וחבלה הכתוב מדבר? ve'eima befitzuyei habat uknasatah vechavalah hakatuv medaber?
How do you know when it's saying that the brothers don't get
rights to the daughter, that's talking about earnings? Maybe they do inherit
the right to the earnings. Maybe the only things that they don't
get from the daughter that the father used to get was like
things like קנס kenas and damages and all those things, which we
said go to the father, right? But maybe other types of thing
because and those things are things that more are fundamentally the girl's.
She's the one that's being injured. They're also less common types of
things. So that's the one that we could say that doesn't transfer
to the brothers. But something like the regular rights of regular earnings,
maybe the same way even biblically that the father was entitled to
it, maybe the brothers get it after the father dies? וכן תנא
רבי חנינא, vechen tana Rabi Chanina, and that's how רבי חנינא Rabi
Chanina explains this case. בפיצויי הבת וקנסה וחבלה הכתוב מדבר. befitzuyei habat
uknasatah vechavalah hakatuv medaber.
We're talking about the sort of payments by קנס kenas and seduction
and injury. And so on. That's a daughter keeps after the father
died. That's her whole משנה Mishna, that after the daughter's father died
the daughter keeps it, but maybe earnings, maybe that does pass on
to the brothers. So the גמרא Gemara first of all before answering
that, okay maybe you can't prove it from that from that case,
maybe it is talking about those things, says one minute. Like it's
going to question the use of the word חבלות Chavalos here, injuries.
חבלות, Chavalos, injuries, צערא דגופא נינהו. Tza'ara degufa ninhu.
Even if the father is alive, she gets payment for if somebody
injures her. Somebody breaks the daughter's arm, right, or whatever, or even
worse. What do you do with the payment for that? Does the
father pocket it or what the גמרא Gemara says is you basically
put it in an escrow account for the girl, right, you invest
the money and you hold on to that money and it really
is belongs to the daughter because it's there for her broken arm.
So the גמרא Gemara now actually says one minute. Obviously that wouldn't
pass on to the brothers. The father doesn't even get it. The
father gets קנס Knas but he doesn't actually get the cost of
injury. Now, you'll say one minute, our משנה, Mishna our משנה's been
saying that he gets בושת Boshes and פגם. Pagam. Yes, בושת Boshes
is embarrassment,
so that's not exactly injury. That we're saying that the father would
be entitled to. פגם, Pagam, remember, what's the פגם? Pagam? That she's
a non-virgin. So now what? So therefore the father can't really sell
her, you know, or marry her off at the same price or
something like that. That's not the same type of an injury that
somebody now is never going to walk again, or somebody's never going
to use their arm again. That is something that is fundamentally, you
know, that person's that you've taken that thing away from that person.
I mean, okay, you'd say the same thing about the virginity but
whatever the גמרא Gemara sees that as different. And therefore
says that that would never go to the father. So why is
this thing suggesting that it would? So the גמרא Gemara says wait
let's see the answer. אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא Amar Rabi Yose
bar Chanina and then you'll say what you want to say. שפצעה
בפניה. Shepatza'ah befaneha.
Basically, you smacked her in the face. It's a type of an
injury. Now what type of an answer is that? So it could
be saying that it's not a permanent injury. A permanent injury the
money would go for the daughters. A non-permanent injury would be like,
you know, I don't know let's say it's a broken arm and
she'll heal or something like that. Or רש"י Rashi suggests the reason
it's different is
no רש"י Rashi doesn't spell out why it's different. He just says
it would affect her price if you were to sell her, but
that's true about other things as well. Okay, but exactly what the
answer is isn't clear. It could be that we're talking about a
non-permanent injury. It could be תוספות Tosafot says that we're talking about
let me take a look.
Yeah, maybe an injury right תוספות Tosafot says an injury that only
lasts during her period of her being a קטנה Ketana and נערה
Na'arah and she'll be healed from it once by the time she's
an adult by the time she's a בוגרת, Bogeret, that goes to
the father. Because the father could have sold her. The father could
have married her and he could have pocketed the money. So if
she now has a broken arm and he can get less for
selling her as a slave, that's his loss. When do we say
the money for the injury is held for her, that's when it's
something that's going to be a permanent injury or go beyond her
being a קטנה Ketana and there it's going to be something that
she's going to lose out, not just the father lose out, besides
of course the fact that she you know the practical aspects but
even in the monetary aspects. Okay so before I get to Michael's
question is the answer clear? Meaning the גמרא Gemara says the father
doesn't pass on the rights to his daughter. Okay and it seems
to be therefore the right to the earnings. The גמרא Gemara. says
ah maybe it only means the rights he has in collecting for
her if she's injured. Okay or if the קנס. Knas. Which then
led to this digression, one minute, does the father really collect for
her in an injury, right? Isn't that injury her own injury? Doesn't
she collect the money for an injury? And the גמרא Gemara distinguishes
between different types of injuries. It's not exactly clear what the line
of distinction is but the easiest way to understand it is a
permanent versus a non-permanent injury. A non-permanent injury the father will collect
because he's going to lose out in terms of his ability to
sell her or to marry her off, but a permanent injury is
something that's much more her loss than his loss and therefore that's
something that she's going to collect for. But we haven't yet proven
that the rights to her earnings doesn't get passed down to the
sons. Michael, you had a question. In terms of in terms of
collecting for injury I'm trying to understand. There's the loss of income
which can be permanent, that I
totally understand goes to her, but what about like you know you
put her in the hospital you have to pay the hospital? That
goes to her? No, but that's different. That's ריפוי. Ripuy. Okay so
he gets that? Yeah, yeah, yeah.
We're only talking about נזק. Nezek.
Rabbi Dov you had a question?
Okay, yeah, it's just the bodily injury to the daughter that she's
carrying that with her for the rest of her life.
Right. Well, the father is even though he can sell her, he's
going to be selling a less valuable right. So that's exactly the
question. Maybe he's entitled to the amount of that loss for the
period he could sell her for and
she's entitled to the rest of the loss. So that's what's not
spelled out in this גמרא. Gemara תוספות Tosafot tries to figure that
out but yes, that's exactly along the lines of the answer. Yes.
I would even say that this distinction indicates to me is that
the father doesn't literally own physically, doesn't own the daughter. Right, she's
not an עבד כנעני, Eved Kena'ani,
she's like an עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. He owns her ma— Okay,
right.
Alright, אמר רב זירא,
Amar Rav Zeira, let's wrap this up, אמר רב זירא אמר רב
מתנה, Amar Rav Zeira Amar Rav Masna, so רב זירא Rav Zeira
said in the name of רב מתנה, Rav Masna, אמר רב Amar
Rav in the name of רב, Rav, ואמרי לה Ve'amrei lah say
אמר רבי זירא אמר
רב מתנה אמר רב,
Amar Rabbi
Zeira Amar
Rav Masna Amar Rav, רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira said it. Now who's
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira as opposed to רב זירא? Rav Zeira? So
רש"י Rashi says they're the same person. The difference is that רבי
זירא Rabbi Zeira was after he got סמיכה semicha in ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. רב זירא Rav Zeira was only when he got the
not real סמיכה semicha in בבל. Bavel. But then he went to
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and got the real סמיכה, semicha, then he
became רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. So the question is at what stage
in his life did he say this? Anyway, באה וניזונית מן האחין
מעשה ידיה לעצמה Ba'ah venizonis min ha'achin ma'aseh yadeha l'atzmah that she
keeps the earnings, דכתיב dechitiv והתנחלתם vehisnachaltem like the same thing we
said before although there's another way to read the verse. והתנחלתם אותם
לבניכם אחריכם Vehisnachaltem osam livneichem achareichem אותם לבניכם Osam livneichem your slaves
you bequeath to your sons ולא בנותיכם לבניכם velo benoseichem livneichem not
your daughters to your sons. מגיד שאינו מוריש זכות בתו לבנו. Magid
she'eino morish zchus bito livno. He does not bequeath the rights he
has, the monetary rights he has in his daughter to his son.
Okay, אמר ליה אבימי בר פפי Amar lei Avimi bar Pappi שקוד
אמרה, Shkod amrah, שקוד Shkod already said it. Who's שקוד? Shkod? So
שקוד מנו Shkod manu who is שקוד? Shkod? שמואל. Shmuel. So שמואל
Shmuel is called שקוד Shkod because רש"י says we פסקן pasken like
שמואל Shmuel in דיני ממונות dinei mamonus because he was very diligent
and a master of that, like to be שוקד, shoked, you know,
to be diligent in your learnings. Anyway, שמואל Shmuel said this. So
this idea that you don't pass it on to the daughter. So
the גמרא Gemara says הא רב אמר, Ha Rav amar, what do
you mean שמואל Shmuel said it? We had before that it was
a tradition of רב. Rav. So it says אימא אף שקוד אמרה.
eima af Shkod amrah. Fine, שמואל Shmuel agrees with רב. Rav. שמואל
Shmuel said the same thing. We're not saying רב Rav didn't say
it but שמואל Shmuel also said it. So the גמרא says אמר
אמי בר מימרא לרב אשי amar Ami bar Meimra l'Rav Ashi הכי
אמרי בנהרדעא. hachi amri be'Naharda'a. Here's what they say in נהרדעא, Naharda'a,
הלכתא כוותיה דרב ששת. Hilchesa kevaseih de'Rav Sheshes. We rule like רב
ששת. Rav Sheshes. רב ששת Rav Sheshes as you'll remember is the
one that said that, tried to say that the daughter was like
the אלמנה, that the same way the widow the earnings go to
the estate, the daughter the earnings go to the estate. So he
actually says we don't rule that way. Right. רב אשי אמר הלכתא
כוותיה דרב.
Rav Ashi amar hilchesa
kevaseih de'Rav. No, we rule like רב Rav who says the daughter
keeps the earnings. והלכתא כוותיה דרב Vehilchesa kevaseih de'Rav and we rule
like רב, Rav, that's where all the evidence has been pointing, that
the daughter unlike the widow the daughter actually does keep her earnings
even and doesn't even give back to the estate the amount that
it costs to, doesn't even replenish the estate for the amount it
costs to support her. So Michael you'll be very happy because the
סוגיא sugya actually ended telling us what the הלכה halacha was. Okay,
let's take a look now. What? We're talking about a נערה, na'arah,
right. What happens if she is still at the estate, does she
continue to be supported? Yeah, I have to double check that. Okay,
yes, I don't remember offhand. Okay, so the גמרא says like this:
המארס את בתו וגירשה. Ham'ares es bito vegerashah. Do we have time?
What time is it? 8:27. Okay, great, we have three minutes. There's
three minutes till the bus comes. Okay. המארס את בתו Ham'ares es
bito 8:27 according to Verizon. המארס את בתו Ham'ares es bito וגירשה.
vegerashah. Somebody basically betrothes his daughter and then she was divorced, he
didn't divorce her. אירסה ונתאלמנה. Irsah venisalmanah. Now the father, remember after
אירוסין eirusin the
daughter is still considered under the control of the father before נישואין.
nisu'in. And if she gets divorced
she reverts to full control of the father.
So the same way he could marry off his daughter as a
קטנה, ketanah, if she only had אירוסין eirusin and then she was
divorced he can remarry her off, she goes back to being under
full control of the father. So he betrothes her and she gets
divorced. אירסה ונתאלמנה. Irsah venisalmanah. Or afterwards he betrothes her and she
became widowed. כתובתה שלו. Kesuvasah shelo. He keeps the כתובה. kesuvah She
never had a נישואין nisu'in so he never lost control over her.
Right, the control of the father is as I said is up
to the point of נישואין. nisu'in. So therefore if he's collecting her
כתובה kesuvah from the ארוס arus that money is going to go
to the father. The same way the father gets all the earnings
of the daughter, right, and injury and אונס ones and קנס knas
and all those things, he's also going to get the כתובה kesuvah
payment. That's going to go to him as well because she's still
under his control, she's still an ארוסה, arusah, or she was an
ארוסה. arusah. Now this assumes that there is כתובה kesuvah payment for
an ארוסה. arusah. That's a debate whether the כתובה kesuvah obligation begins
at the time of אירוסין eirusin or even time of נישואין. nisu'in.
This is obviously assuming it begins at the time of אירוסין. eirusin.
Okay, now let's say it's not אירוסין. eirusin. Okay. השיאה וגירשה. Hisi'ah
vegerashah. He actually brought her to the stage of נישואין nisu'in and
then she got divorced. השיאה ונתאלמנה Hisi'ah venisalmanah and then she remarried
herself at that stage because she's free from the father and then
she became widowed. כתובתה שלה. Kesuvasah shelah. She collects both of those
כתובות kesuvos because once she hit נישואין nisu'in she was in her
own control or her husband's control but out of her father's control.
And therefore she's going to collect the כתובה from the נישואין. nisu'in.
רבי יהודה אומר הראשונה של אב. Rabbi Yehuda omer harishonah shel av.
No, actually the first payment for the first wedding the father will
collect. Okay, so that's interesting because basically that means that all כתובות,
kesuvos, right, all first marriages, this is a crazy idea. Think what
he's just saying. Well, not all first marriages. Basically if the father,
excuse me, I didn't make it clear. The father did קידושי קטנה.
kidushei ketanah. Okay, you got it? The father married her off to
ראובן. Reuven. Okay, so he got the wedding started. He got the
wedding started, he got the marriage started. Then it led to נישואין
*Nissuin*, okay? So think again, if there would never been נישואין *Nissuin*,
the father married her to ראובן *Reuven* and then she got divorced
and got the כתובה *Ksuva*, everybody agrees who would collect the כתובה
*Ksuva*? The father. So now it's a debt basically that the father
would collect. Now that אירוסין *Erusin* became sort of like a, whatever,
been converted into a נישואין *Nissuin*, right? Does the debt now go
away from the father, right, because that's where it started because the
father married her as a קטנה *Ketana*? But now that there's נישואין
*Nissuin* and now that she's in her, she's away from the father's
control, does the debt come directly to her? Or does it remain
towards the father? Does her age matter? No, נישואין *Nissuin* is like
בוגרת *Bogeres*, נישואין *Nissuin* is like בוגרת *Bogeres*. She becomes totally free
from the father. Yes. Right. So רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* is saying
if the father married her off and did the אירוסין *Erusin*, then
even after the נישואין *Nissuin*, the father's still going to collect her
כתובה *Ksuva*. Okay? Yeah. רבי יהודה אומר *Rabbi Yehuda Omer*, ראשונה של
אב *Rishona Shel Av*. אמרו לו *Amru Lo*, they said to him,
משהשיאה אין אבי רשות בה *Mishehisiya en avi reshus bah*. I'm sorry.
Once she had נישואין *Nissuin*, the father loses any rights, even if
he had rights to the כתובה *Ksuva* from before the נישואין *Nissuin*,
he loses it once the נישואין *Nissuin* took place. Okay? We'll just
read one line in the גמרא *Gemara*, 8:29, we have one minute.
And because the גמרא *Gemara* makes a side point before we get
to the meat of the משנה *Mishna*. טעמא דהשיאה וגירשה השיאה ונתאלמנה
*Taama dihisiya vegirsha hisiya venis'almla*, it says the משנה *Mishna* gave scenarios
that first the husband divorced her and then the husband died. Why
didn't it give a scenario that there were two deaths? Right? It
just wanted to give a scenario of two weddings. Why did it
have one as a divorce and one as a death? Why not
give one of two deaths? אבל נתאלמנה תרי זימני לא חזיא לאינסבא
*Aval nis'almla trei zimnei lo chaziya le'insa*. It did not want to
give the scenario of two deaths because if two husbands had died
on her, we would, she would no longer be fit to remarry
a third guy. Why? Because that's a debate. There's a debate that
if a woman's husbands keep on dying on her, do we assume
that something's up that makes the husbands die, and that she can't
get remarried? And if so, is it after two times or after
three times? So the גמרא *Gemara* says, אגב אורחא *Agav orcha*, קסבר
תנא כרבי *Kasavar tana ke-Rabbi*, and just in passing our משנה *Mishna*
is going like רבי *Rabbi*, דאמר בתרי זימני הוה חזקה *D'amar bitrei
zimnei havei chazaka*. Once something happened two times in a row, we
have to start being concerned about it, and if two husbands died
on her in a row, then we're going to say that she
can't get remarried because we're assuming that something's up that's making her
husbands die on her. She's some type of a black widow case.
Okay, anyway, that was a side point. We'll continue with the meat
of this משנה *Mishna* tomorrow. Like the seven sons that die from
a, yes, similar, that's it.